# *RESUME* Kim H. Sundeen

Address:

8335 Half Moon Dr. Iron River, WI 54847 **Contact Information:** 

Phone: 218-590-1330

E-mail: kim.h.sundeen@gmail.com

# CAREER OBJECTIVES

To research, plan, implement, & direct novel GIS systems, applications, and services to improve the mapping effectiveness and experience of any GIS user or non-GIS user's with understanding spatial information for personal or work projects.

#### EDUCATION

#### University of WI-Madison, WI

Master of Science: Geographic Information Systems/Cartography—Web Map Programming

**Anticipated Completion: Summer 2018** 

#### **Continuing Education**

## **Programming**

Ongoing - SQL Server Database, PHP, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, & JQuery self-taught training completed online using <u>W3schools.com</u>, <u>KhanAcademy.org</u>, & <u>Lynda.com</u>

2015 - Pennsylvania State's online self-paced course, GEOG 585, "Open Web Mapping"

2015 & 2016 - WLIA Annual Conf. 4-hour workshop: "Advanced Python" & "Python Classes"

2015 - Annual Conf. MN GIS/LIS 4-hour workshops: "ArcGIS for Javascript API"

2015 - Annual Conf. MN GIS/LIS 4-hour workshops: "Using Geoprocessing Services with the ArcGIS Javascript API"

2014 & 2016 - WLIA Annual Conf. 4-hour workshop: "Introduction to Python for ArcGIS 10.x"

2013 - eGIS Associates' "Introduction to the ArcGIS Javascript API Online," & "Introduction to OpenLayers," (3 days)

#### **ArcGIS for Server & SDE Geodatabase Management**

2013 - Esri's "ArcGIS for Server: Site Configuration & Administration," (3 days);

2013 - Esri's "ArcGIS for Server: Sharing GIS Content on the Web," (2 days)

2013 - Esri's "Configuring & Managing the Multiuser Geodatabase." (3 days)

#### University of WI-Madison, WI

#### **Graduate Certificate: Geographic Information Systems**

Aug. 2012; 3.9/4.0 GPA

**Internship Focus:** Spatial prediction of mercury concentration in the Great Lakes drainage basins from stream water quality data & remotely-sensed leaf area index as input for climate hydrologic models using Python & R languages.

#### Master of Science: Conservation Biology & Sustainable Development

December, 2011; 3.4/4.0 GPA

Thesis: Using R to model and predict sandhill crane & power line collision risk in agricultural-wetland landscapes in WI.

**Bachelor of Science: Wildlife Ecology, Certificate: Environmental Studies** 

May, 2006; 3.2/4.0 GPA

## WORK EXPERIENCE

# GIS Programmer Analyst, GIS & Facility Operations, MN Power, Duluth, MN

(April 2016-Present)

Coordinated dev. & test Web AppBuilder installations; documented workflows for designing & publishing custom Survey123, Arc Collector, and WebMaps; trained staff on using Model Builder, Python, & ArcGIS Online with existing utility editing, work order, & field tools systems.

# GIS Specialist, City of Duluth, Engineering Division, Duluth, MN

(Feb. 2015-April 2016)

Coordinated full lifecycle software & database development for mapping & web data-entry applications with Python & ArcGIS Online. Managed editing, training, and metadata tools for versioned SQL Server SDE database editing practices.

## GIS Specialist, Bad River Tribe, Natural Resources Dept., Odanah, WI

(Oct 2012-Feb. 2015)

Organized & designed GIS data in databases for all depts., planned & published data-entry webmaps, & updated tribal website.

#### Sr. Natural Resources Research Scientist, WI Dept. of Natural Resources, Madison, WI

(May 2012-Oct 2012)

Analyzed & organized water quality data for input into linear regression models using Python, ArcGIS & opensource GIS & mapping tools.

## Web/GIS Technician, State Cartographer's Office, University of WI-Madison: Madison, WI

(May 2012-Oct 2012)

Customized Python scripts & add-ins to create natural basemaps of WI & updating the Cartographer's website.

#### GIS Project Assistant, School of Nursing, University of WI-Madison: Madison, WI

(Jan. 2010-Oct 2012)

Page 1

Developed Python algorithms to compare water quality interpolated data related to how map readers perceived their water quality risk.

<u>Biologist/GIS Specialist—Student Temp. Ed. Program, US Geological Survey, Madison, WI</u> (Oct. 2011-May 2012)

Entered & evaluated data in one of the largest vector spatial SQL Server databases with the USFWS' National Wetlands Inventory.

Resume—Kim Sundeen Pag

# PROJECT & PERSONNEL MANAGEMENT

- **Full Cycle Project Development & Implementation:** Coordinated GIS User Needs Assessment & Implementation Plans for 19 projects for software development, database development/improvements, training, & website improvements for City of Duluth IT Dept. & Public Works & Utilities Dept beginning in 2015.
- **Training:** Taught introductory Python, JavaScript, GPS & GIS sessions for small group workshops on: (1) using new mapping & GPS programs (2) testing software including ArcGIS Desktop & opensource QGIS, (3) setting up development environments for Python & JavaScript, (4) process for updating website front ends, & (5) GIS user needs assessments.
- **Staff Supervision:** Oversaw & trained student GIS technicians on GIS data entry procedures for UW Nursing School mapping projects & LTE staff for short-term land ownership projects with the Bad River Tribe.
- **Grant Writing:** Received several grants to fund M.Sc. research & provide professional development: \$10,000 from the *Animal Welfare Institute (2010)*; Additional \$1,025 from research organizations for mapping (2010-2011); \$5,200 from *ESRI for ArcMap online training through the Conservation Grant Program (2012);* \$127,000 from the Federal Emergency Management Agency Pre-Disaster Mitigation Program.
- **GIS Data Security:** Implemented new ArcGIS Server security protocol for publishing GIS services online; Researched & rewrote external & internal data-sharing agreements & policies for the Bad River Tribe.

# DATA MANAGEMENT & PROGRAMMING KNOWLEDGE

#### **Database & Data Structures Management:**

- Awarded a **\$127,000** grant from the FEMA Pre-Disaster Mitigation Program for planning & implementing a webenabled database to deliver interactive webmaps & identify natural disaster risks for community planning meetings.
- Implemented new ArcGIS Server & published GIS secured web services for the Bad River Tribe; Expanded existing GIS map services to multiuser, versioned online feature editing & Python-built geoprocessing services for City of Duluth.
- Managed multiuser editing in ArcGIS 10.x SDE databases-2008/2013 Microsoft SQL Server for Tribe & City since 2012.

#### **Programming:**

- Created Python routines to download & extract ArcGIS Online data & images from a Survey123 app & export to a PDF with hyperlinked images and a summary of data from multiple related tables within a geodabase.
- Developed Python-based geoprocessing services to take web entry to update the SQL Server database & ArcGIS Server.
- Script opensource & ArcGIS programs to manipulate, re-write, or edit raster & vector data for use in GIS analysis & remote sensing apps (batch-processing image enhancements & transforms, & radiometric/atmospheric correction).
- Used spatial statistics & mapping programming modules in R to develop regression algorithms for predicting mercury in watersheds for drainage basins from water quality data & remotely-sensed leaf area index (LAI).

## Web Development:

- Developed, tested, trained staff, & implemented customized GIS services & geoprocessing tools through ArcGIS Server for mobile data entry & data-transfer through ArcGIS Online webmaps for the Tribe, City of Duluth, & MN Power.
- Added new HTML/CSS pages for reorganizing the Bad River Tribal Natural Resources webpage to host both secured & public Google, Esri JavaScript API, ArcGIS Online, & GeoMoose OpenLayers webmaps: <a href="www.badriver-nsn.gov/tribal-operations/natural-resources/gis-maps">www.badriver-nsn.gov/tribal-operations/natural-resources/gis-maps</a>

## SOFTWARE

Databases: Microsoft (SQL Server 2008/2013, SQL Server Express, & MS Access), Oracle, ArcSDE & PostgreSQL

GIS/GPS: ArcGIS 9.3-10.3.1., ArcGIS Pro, QGIS 1.6-2.16, Google Earth, ArcPad 7.1 & 10.2, Terrasync 5.6, & Pathfinder Office 5.4

**Statistics/Remote Sensing:** ENVI, IDRISI, R, SPSS, Systat, S-PLUS, OpenEV, Opticks **Programming:** HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Python (Arcpy, OGR, GDAL, & modules)

Code Versioning: TortoiseShell SVN, Github

**Presentation/Design:** Adobe Illustrator & Photoshop 2015.5; & Microsoft 7 & 10 OS Office, Prezi, Slides.com, reveal.js **Project Management:** Agile Methodoogy-Scrum framework in Basecamp, MindManager, Freedcamp, Windows OneNote

Web Content Management Systems: Joomla, Druple, WordPress, Bluehost

## VOLUNTEER POSITIONS

MN GIS/LIS Conference Planning Team: *St. Paul, MN*Wember; Workshop Planning Committee
WI Land Information Association: *Madison, WI*National Tribal Geog. Info. Support Center: *Albuquerque, NM*Board Member; Chair Membership Committee
Publications Committee Member
2015-Present
Publications Committee Member
2013-2014

## PERSONAL INTERESTS

Geocaching, Birding, Canoeing, Skiing, Piano, Jazz music, Singing Phantom of the Opera songs

Please see my website <a href="https://ksundeen.github.io">https://ksundeen.github.io</a>

Resume—Kim Sundeen Page 2